# Mohit Vaishnav

LinkedIn Google scholar mohit.vaishnav@gmail.com Personal Website

#### **SUMMARY**

Broadly my research revolves around exploring different aspects of the abstract reasoning abilities forms the core of intelligence in both humans and animals and incorporating them into machines. I have more than 5 years of experience in developing Deep Neural Networks for Computer Vision and medical imaging for both academia and industries.

#### **EDUCATION**

# **Doctor of Philosophy**

Oct 2019 - Apr 2023

Serre Lab, Brown University, USA

Artificial and Natural Intelligence Toulouse Institute (ANITI), France

Thesis: Exploring the role of self-attention in cognitive and computer vision architectures

Supervisor: Thomas Serre (Professor, Brown University, USA)

### **Erasmus Joint Masters**

Sept 2017 - 2019

Computer VIsion and RoBOTics (VIBOT)

Semester 1: University of Bourgogne, France (CGPA: 15.1/20)

Semester 2: University of Girona, Spain (CGPA: 9/10)

Semester 3: Heriot-Watt University, UK (CGPA: 75.6/100)

**Thesis**: MU-Net: A deep learning model for teeth segmentation from X-ray images

Supervisor: Hugues Talbot (Professor, CentraleSupèlèc, France)

# Bachelor of Technology (Hons.)

July 2009 - 2013

2019

2018

Electronics and Communication Engineering

LNM Institute of Information Technology, Jaipur, India (CGPA: 7.89/10.00),

Thesis: Residue coding technique for video compression

Supervisor: A. K. Tiwari (Assoc. Professor, Indian Institute of Technology, Jodhpur, India)

## AREA OF INTEREST

Artificial Intelligence, Computational Neuroscience, Visual reasoning, Computer Vision, Classification, Attention and Memory process, Cognitive science, Machine Intelligence

## INDUSTRIAL EXPERIENCE

- WeDiagnostiX, Paris, France: Masters Thesis with a Dental AI startup where I developed first working prototype for the classification/understanding of maxillary structures from X-ray imaging using Deep learning. My responsibilities included creating an end-to-end pipeline, starting with data collection and labeling till building a working prototype.
- Quelia Systems Inc., Paris, France: During the summer internship, I was tasked to build an application for estimating tyre wear using a portable mobile camera and computer vision technique. With the software developed, any person can approximate the depth of the treads and accordingly take action to replace them if needed.
- Indian Institute of Technology, Jodhpur, India: Worked as a Research assistant with a task to develop lossless video compression techniques with Prof. Anil Kumar Tiwari.

# STARTUP EXPERIENCE

| mines and played a key role in overseeing the day-to-day operations of the firm supervising 20 employees and has made significant contributions to the efficiency and productivity of our team.                   | 201110      |
|---|-------------|
| - Kevin Technology, Ajmer, India: Co-founded a start-up with a vision to develop surveillance system based on computer vision techniques.   | 2016-17     |
| SUMMER INTERNSHIPS  |             |
| - Contributed to <b>Kumbhathon</b> for innovating the Kumbha festival by MIT USA and developed an algorithm for "Abnormal Motion Detection"   | 2015        |
| - Undergraduate Summer Research Internship at Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore (India), under the supervision of Prof. K. R. Ramakrishnan and worked on 3D Video Synopsis: Capturing to Transmission | 2012        |
| - Undergraduate Summer Research Internship at Global Internship Program In Engineering Innovation And Design Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Delhi (India), where I wrote a review on compression sensing.   | 2011        |
| - Undergraduate Summer Research Internship at Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Jodhpur (India), under the supervision of Prof. A. K. Tiwari and worked on developing lossless video compression techniques.  | 2010        |
| TEACHING EXPERIENCE   |             |
| - Taught Basics of Introduction to Computer vision at the Federal University of Toulouse Midi-Pyrènèes, France  | 2021,'22    |
| - Taught <i>Visual Reasoning in Computer Vision</i> at the Federal University of Toulouse Midi-Pyrènèes, France   | 2021,'22    |
| - Supervised 15 M1 students at Paul Sabatier University, France for the course Initiation to research work (project) (EMINC2B2),  | 2021        |
| - Teaching Assistant for Electronics lab at LNMIIT, India   | 2010-12     |
| CONFERENCE TALKS  |             |
| - Ivan Felipe, Thomas Fel, Mohit Vaishnav, Peter Wilf, Thomas Serre, "Using Artificial Intelligence To Identify Fossil Angiosperm Leaves At Family Level", Geological Society of America, Connects, Denver (USA)  | 2022        |
| - Mohit Vaishnav, Thomas Fel, Ivan Felipe, Jacob A Rose, Peter Wilf, Thomas Serre, "Understanding how deep neural networks categorize living and fossil leaves", <i>Botany</i> (virtual)                          | 2021        |
| - Ivan Felipe, Jacob A Rose, Thomas Fel, Mohit Vaishnav, Peter Wilf, Thomas Serre, "A deep-learning-based approach for automated fossil leaf identification", Botany (virtual)                                    | 2021        |
| - Computational models of visual reasoning at <i>Brown Unconference</i>   | 2021        |
| LEADERSHIP POSITION   |             |
| - Elected as Student representative for ANITI, France   | 2020-22     |
| <ul> <li>Elected Member of Senate, Science and Tech. Council, LNMIIT, India</li> <li>Founder and Membership head, IEEE Student branch, LNMIIT, India</li> </ul>   | 2013 $2012$ |
| - Founder and Organizer, Technical Festival <i>Plinth</i> , LNMIIT, India   | 2012        |

- Shree Bherunath Granite, Rajsamad, India: Helped my family setup granite

2014-16

#### HONORS AND AWARDS

- Reviewer Task: IEEE Transaction on Evolutionary Computation 2012,

- Selected in Govt. of India, National fellowship scheme, Kishor Vaigyanic Protsahan Yojna funded by DST, in Engineering stream

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- Mohit Vaishnav, Thomas Serre; "GAMR: Guided Attention Model of (visual) Reasoning." The Eleventh International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) https://openreview.net/forum?id=iLMgk2IGNyv (2023)
- Aimen Zerroug, **Mohit Vaishnav**, Julien Colin, Sebastian Musslick, Thomas Serre; "A Benchmark for Compositional Visual Reasoning." In Proceedings of the Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Track on Datasets and Benchmarks (2022)
- Mohit Vaishnav, Remi Cadene, Andrea Alamia, Drew Linsley, Rufin VanRullen, Thomas Serre; "Understanding the Computational Demands Underlying Visual Reasoning." In Special Collection CogNet of *Neural Computation*; doi: https://doi.org/10.1162/neco\_a\_01485 (2022)
- Mohit Vaishnav, Thomas Fel, Ivan Felipe, Thomas Serre; "Convilormer: Convolutionally guided Vision Transformer." ArXiv abs//2208.08900 (2022)
- Mohit Vaishnav, Binny Tewani and Anil Kumar Tiwari; "Residue coding technique for video compression", 24<sup>th</sup> IEEE *Data Compression Conference (DCC)* (2014), Snowbird, UT, USA, doi: 10.1109/DCC.2014.92
- Mohit Vaishnav and Anil Kumar Tiwari; "Bin classification using temporal gradient estimation for lossless video coding", 24<sup>th</sup> IEEE Data Compression Conference (DCC) (2014), Snowbird, UT, USA, doi: 10.1109/DCC.2014.93
- Mohit Vaishnav, Dinesh Kumar Chobey, and Anil Kumar Tiwari; "Temporal Stationarity Based Prediction Method For Lossless Video Coding". In Proceedings of the 2014 Indian Conference on Computer Vision Graphics and Image Processing (ICVGIP). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 39, 16. https://doi.org/10.1145/2683483.2683522
- Dinesh Kumar Chobey, **Mohit Vaishnav** and Anil Kumar Tiwari; "An optimal switched adaptive prediction method for lossless video coding", 23<sup>rd</sup> IEEE *Data Compression Conference (DCC)* (2013), Snowbird, UT, USA, doi: 10.1109/DCC.2013.63
- Mohit Vaishnav, Ashwani Sharma and Anil Kumar Tiwari; "A noble computationally efficient motion compensation method based on pixel by pixel prediction", 21<sup>st</sup> IEEE Data Compression Conference (DCC) (2011), Snowbird, UT, USA, doi: 10.1109/DCC.2011.83

#### **SKILLS**

- Programming Languages

Python Shell C C++

- Data Science

- Tools & OS

Pytorch Tensorflow/Keras Scikit-Learn Numpy Pandas MATLAB Git Jupyter Vim VSCode Linux MacOs